For the second part of the task, we are asked
to give a flat state diagram of our puzzle.
For that, we need to first think about what
a state could look like, what the starting
state is, what states are reached from the
starting state and so on.
We’ll try to explore all reachable states
and the transitions between them.
Not just the chain of states that would
lead to a goal
but all the states.
And we are told we do not need to label the transitions
necessarily.
I might or might not label them, we will see
how it goes.
First of all, I am going to move the solution
from our first part up to the corner here.
So, we have a little reminder for our rules.
And then, we need to think about what every
state should look like.
The simplest solution here is to just use
a single letter for every actor and the boat
and the river.
And then we end up with basically a little
string for every node
and that shows us what the state
is like.
I am going to put a little glossary over here
on the side.
We are going to use
the vertical line character as the river.
Because it kind of nicely shows us where everybody
is, so being on the left side of this character
is on the left side or the starting side of
the river and being on the right side would
be being on the goal side of the river.
We are going to use the upper-case B for the
boat and upper-case F for the fisherman.
And we are going to be lazy here and use the
V for father.
Because otherwise we are going to end up with
another F here and a small f might be a little
confusing.
So, we just kind of basically take a note
from the German version of this and use V
for Vater, the German father, in this
case.
And we are going to use the lower case c for each
child.
So, we are going to end up with 2 c’s in
each state.
You could also change this of course.
This is not necessarily the letter that is
supposed to be in here.
You could even use numbers if you will although
that might make it a little bit confusing.
Now, for our starting state we need everybody
on the left side of the river.
So, we are going to use the pipe character
to indicate the river and then just put all
the other letters on the left of it.
This tells us that the fisherman, the father,
both children and the boat are on the left
side of the river.
And to indicate that this is our starting
state, we need to put this arrow pointing
at it coming from nowhere.
This is just an index for signifying that
this is the starting state.
And then, from this state we need to think
which states are reachable.
So, which states are reachable.
So, what transitions are possible from here.
First of all, one child can move on
its own.
So, one child crosses together with the boat
to the other side.
Giving us with the fisherman, the father,
one child on one side of the river.
And the child and the boat that crossed over
on the other side.
From here the only possible thing is for the
child to go back.
And our transitions ends up with this double
arrow here.
This is going to be all our transitions state
diagrams.
Because no matter what state we are in it
is always possible to go back to the previous
state.
There are no other possibilities from here.
So, we move on with the other possibilities
from the starting state.
From the starting state the father can also
move over on its own.
This is also not going to lead to the goal.
But this is a state that we need to consider.
Because we are told to consider all reachable
states.
And this leaves us with the fisherman and
both children on one side and the father and
the boat on the other side.
Nothing else is possible here.
Except for the father to move back.
So, we move on with the next possible state
from the starting state, which is the fisherman
moving over on his own.
Which is also not really helpful.
Giving us the father and both children in
the starting side and the fisherman with his
boat on the goal side.
Now the only way to move towards the goal here
would be the final possible transition from
the starting state.
Which is both children crossing together,
which leaves us with the father and the fisherman
on one side and both children on the other.
From here there are only two possible states,
one is both children moving back.
So, coming back to the starting state and
one child crossing alone.
This is also a good place to point out why
we used one character for both children and
not two different characters for two different
daughters.
Because as we pointed out on the first part
of the task, the daughters are functionally
identical in terms of this task.
And using different characters for them here
would just massively complicate the state
diagram without any real benefit.
Because then we’ll end up with C and D for
example for every daughter.
And then from the starting state, we would
have the case where the first daughter moves
on her own.
And a state where the second daughter moves
So, this is an additional state from the starting
state.
And a lot of different states going further.
Because they all kind of branch out more than
necessary here.
In terms of the task here, it is only important
that one child can cross on her own.
And which one it is doesn't really matter.
We know that one is left on one side and the
other is left on the other side.
One crosses alone, and they are basically
interchangeable here.
So, we do not need to complicate this by using
different letters for the 2 daughters.
Going back to this state.
We have one daughter crossing alone.
So, this gives us: the fisherman, the father,
one daughter and the boat on the starting
side.
And one daughter left alone on the goal side.
From here the graph can branch out basically.
Because from here it is possible that either
the fisherman crosses on his own.
Giving us this state of father and one child
on one side.
And the fisherman, the child and the boat
on the other side or the father crossing on
his own.
Leaving us with the fisherman and the child
on one side.
And the father, the boat and the child on
the goal side.
And this pattern kind of repeats here.
Because from here on both sides, one
child can cross on her own.
Or, of course, the father can move back but
this is just a backwards transition or the
fisherman can move backwards but this is just
another backwards transition as well.
So, from here the new transitions to consider
here are the children one child crossing on
her own.
So, on one side this gives us the father,
both children and the boat on the starting
side.
And the fisherman now left alone on the goal
And on the other side it is basically just
always the father or the fisherman reversed
here or swapped rather.
Of course, from this point now both children
could cross together.
Or one child could move back.
Or one of the adults could cross on its own.
And this basically gives us a swapped transition
here where we can cross over into another
part of the path that we might attempt to
go.
So, when the father crosses on his own or
the fisherman crosses on his own.
It is the same resulting state here.
Both children are left alone on the starting
side.
And both adults are on the goal side.
Now moving on from this state there is nothing
possible.
Except backwards transitions.
So, moving on here.
We have both children crossing at once.
Once again on both of these transitions here.
On one side that leaves us with the father
on his own.
And the fisherman and the boat and the two
children on the other side.
And on the other side it is once again just
mirrored here.
This is now the fisherman left on the starting
side.
And the father and both children on the goal
We also have this transition over here again,
where we could move over to the other side
of the solution path.
And I am going to go and skip ahead a little
bit here.
I am going to scroll down a little bit, sorry.
One child can cross on her own.
Giving us these two states.
And then the adults
can transition on their own.
Leaving us with one child on one side, the
fisherman, the father and the child and the
boat on the goal side.
Now from here there are no further
possibilities over here.
Because now we have the children separated
again on the side.
So, they cannot cross together; this is not
possible from either of these states.
And the only possibilities here are the backwards
transition or the transition that we already
have.
The child moving back.
Or the father crossing over or here once again,
the child moving back and the fisherman crossing
over.
So, from here we are going towards the solution
again.
Or we are going further towards the solution
now with the one child crossing on her own.
Giving us both children on one side with the
boat and the adults on the goal side.
And from here the children can cross together
with the boat.
And give us everybody on the goal side.
Now at this point you might forget “hey,
the fisherman and his boat need to go back
to the starting point as we discovered in
the story.
And marked in our solution for the first part
of the task”.
So, just marking this as the goal would be
an error here so we need to keep going a little
bit.
Which are the possibilities that do not lead
us to the goal first of all.
So, we do not forget anything, which is the
father moving back alone which does not lead
us anywhere.
Or one child moving back on her own, which
does not lead us anywhere either.
And finally, the fisherman taking his boat
back to the starting side giving us the goal
state which is the fisherman and the boat
at the starting side.
And the father and both children at the goal
side.
And this dash line around it here signifies
that this is the final state.
Now, as I mentioned before.
Your graph might not necessarily need to look
exactly the same as this.
This is just one way to draw the graph and
this kind of looks very tidy.
Because going down goes towards the goal state.
And we have this parallel pathway in the middle
here.
But if yours ends up looking differently that
is not a big deal, as long as the information
is correct.
And all the states are correct you can even-
like I said in the beginning, you can swap
up the letters as well.
These particularities of that are not really
important.
As long as all the states are technically
correct.